okay this is a little video to talk
about insight what it means to incite
emergent capacities and how it relates
in some respect to developmental stages
developmental capacities in how it
doesn't relate to the what we usually
think of as developmental stages or
developmental capacities now what I want
to use in terms of stage theory is some
of you may be familiar with Fisher's
skill set theory skill theory of
development and it represents what I
call a theory that's based on a natural
hierarchy in other words there are no
assumptions about progress in his theory
the the stages are based upon a natural
hierarchy so natural hierarchy is
something for example you have to be two
feet tall before you can get to be three
feet tall you have to be three feet tall
before you can get to be four feet tall
natural hierarchy would be in Fisher
sets that you have to be able to handle
systems before you can handle systems of
systems so natural hierarchy is is
really just a hierarchy by definition
not by any assumptions of what is higher
or lower in levels so I really attracted
to developmental theories that do not
have a developmental bias in them but
are the hierarchy comes out of just a
natural hierarchy natural hierarchy has
got to be two years old before you can
be three years old these are these are
hierarchies that are just natural or
trivial by definition
so Fisher's skill set theory starts with
around three to four months we have
skills that he calls single actions so a
toddler a new toddler might reach for
something so that would be us a single
action and we could just make a dot
there and then around seventy seven to
eight months
Fisher calls simple mapping so you might
take this action and you map it to you
know you map it to your pet rabbit or
something so you have a you have simple
mappings around seven to eight months
and then so you reach for another pet
and you have a different type of toy
let's say and you map on that the next
stage he calls systems so you have
simple systems and they emerge around
eleven to thirteen months so you might
then take this and have a system that in
your mind is a system of toys so then
you can reach if this action is reach
you can reach for toys they're no longer
the action is no longer mapped onto a
simple rep simple thing but on to a
system you can your mom can tell you to
play with your toys so there are simple
systems then the this this set of
actions skills then gets reiterated as
representations so now we're going into
something less concrete in more
representation so around two years you
have you'll see the
similarity single representations and
then you have mappings of
representations and then you have
systems of representations and by the
time you get the systems of reputations
you're out around six to seven years old
and then the third level is a level of
abstractions and so there's single
abstractions
there's mapping of abstractions and
there are their systems of abstractions
that brings us anyway up to 23 to 25
years that this is emerging so what
happens is over time then what we have
is a cognitive capacity that is grown
into complexity so some of these things
are systems and we can make systems of
systems some of these actually represent
systems so this would be a meta system
and then there's mappings on to each
other there's mapping into a system as
whole things map onto concept concepts
map onto abstractions and we have what
it what could be the whole cognitive or
metaphysical framework of the individual
and this can grow from systems thinking
as common sense to meta systemic so
you've been able to organize this
systems of systems to paradigmatic Pig
Matic so you can take systems of systems
and organize them into paradigms and
then you can actually get to be meta
paradigmatic
so this is by the time we are gone
through enough cognitive development and
skillset development and language
development then the framework that
we're dealing with our belief systems
our action inquiry system can be quite
complex so I want to talk about the
difference between inspiration and
insight from this theory skit from this
skill set theory so if we have and I'll
just do a simple grid here all of these
represent depending on what scale are
you are they could be systems so this
could be a mapping of systems or could
be a mapping of representations it could
be a mapping of actions whatever level
of complexity who have this whole thing
is your paradigm okay the actual
metaphysical paradigm that you're
operating under that organizes reality
for you in a very very complex way and
when someone if you add inspiration to
it then what I think you do is you learn
how you can actually build on this
further so you can end up creating some
kind of larger synthesis and and build
on your paradigm through inspiration so
and just another caveat I believe that
Fisher's skill set theory works for a
certain type of mind that dialectic
dualistic mind there are cultural
studies that show that intellectual
sophistication does not
in fact have to grow this way but that's
just a caveat so if we but if we stick
with this way of organizing intellectual
sophistication and cognitive skill
incapacity developmental capacity once
we have a paradigm we operated under
certain paradigm and we have inspiration
we can build on that paradigm we learn
how to build new entities completely new
ideas new mappings new entities to
problem-solve but if we add insight
insight is less developmental so this is
a developmental progression it's more
transformative and it has a very strong
deconstruction they've added dynamic to
it so in what insight does is the that
you have the organism has this paradigm
much of it has by now is very
unconscious and yet the organism is
trying to solve problems the organism
the human being is in constant adaptive
tension and trying to solve problems
trying to look for more adaptive fit
trying to decrease suffering and
increase freedom and at some point
there's an experience that happens in
which one of these prior entities okay
one of these let's say one of these
mappings or one of these systems or one
of these actions that got interpreted in
a certain way all of a sudden the
insight is that either this is a false
mapping and it might or there's some
trauma that might be associated with it
or that the mapping is arbitrary and not
and and so that there's other options to
the way this mapping and its
ramifications could be the
they are that the mapping is arbitrary
or it's based on conditions that are
limiting limiting conditions so for
example there's that great movie of
William Randolph Hearst and he maps his
the word rosebud onto his sleigh and
that becomes a system of emotional
trauma that stays with him forever by
the time he builds on that system then
he's operating under a paradigm of
paranoia and and very very high
competitive action logics so insight
what insight does is somehow the
organism realizes that there is malware
or there is an error deep inside this
huge paradigm and what happens then is
that there's a shift that happens this
whole mapping this whole system gets
reorganized and it gets reorganized for
example let's say it gets reorganized
like this so now it's a different type
of system and then all the other ways
that all the other ideas abstractions
assumptions that have been built up on
this have to then fall into place in
different ways because they were all all
these other mappings were correct or
efficient mappings but now that
something in here has been reorganized
then the entire system gets reorganized
and all these kinds of insights the new
insights cascade and new systems new
systems of systems cascade out of this
the deconstruction of this part of this
whole architecture of reality so
that's what in insight is an insight
works at this level and I did have a
conversation with Zach Stein who was you
know one of fishers students and is
working in developmental theory here and
he did say that insight isn't is not
doesn't is not part of this dynamic it's
it's it's when you have a an insight
into something that was prior previously
laid down gets shifted and
reconstruction reconstructed so that the
architecture then shifts along with it
so now in terms of developmental theory
if we have this architecture and this is
going to relate this to developmental
theory and collective insight if we have
this architecture and let's say this is
one person and this is another person
and this person has a simpler
architecture is not working at a meta
system systemic level this person is
working at a meta systemic level and
this one's working at a system level
let's say and let's say that their
constructs are mapped here very the
constructs above let's say the the
systemic level here
they just don't appear for this person
so if the process is working to
disambiguate or to shift some
assumptions in this territory then of
course there's going to be no
contribution here but the higher or the
the more complex the assumption the the
shallower the insight so an insight that
happens
deep in this architecture has the power
to shift much more the architecture then
an insight higher up so these would be
anything that shifts higher up in
complexity represents makes us makes a
less significant change in the
architecture now there is some downward
causation so for example a person could
have an insight at the conceptual level
that then requires something and deeper
in the deeper levels must shift but most
transformation does not happen that way
most transformation most organisms most
people resist having structures that are
more complex transform deeper more
embodied structures so there is a
component here but in general the
biggest insights are deeper in the
architecture of the cognition or the
organism so so if we're looking to
transform some basic collective insights
that a basic human level then the
tension between the way this person
assumptions and architecture have been
drawn in this person's architecture have
been drawn will produce authentic chaos
so instead of the organism itself trying
to find adaptive fit there is something
about being a collective process where
this system this collective system has
some kind of incoherence here because
the mapping is different and so the both
individuals the system tries to find a
new coherence at a very deep level and
and when that happens then the the the
architecture of both
individuals have to shift so that this
is innocence developmentally dependent
depending upon if you're working for
we're looking for insights at higher and
higher capacities but on the other hand
let's say the the individual that has
many more layers of architecture and
meaning that have built on an inherent
instability at a lower level so this
person that is working at a higher
conceptual level but if the instability
or the error the confusion is in this
low level than in some cases in some
cases this person has more complex
resources to avoid this transformation
because is created layers and layers and
layers of strategies to try to make this
fit and some and sometimes can actually
be further away from being able to
incite this transformation than someone
who in this case is in a sense closer to
the actual problem and perhaps has been
sticking with this confusion
energetically in a way that this person
has not now again to reiterate the
advantage though the higher developed
person has is there is a chance to work
downward causation to so to find to
discover that the the confusion in the
conceptual the meta systemic level is
actually arisen from a deeper confusion
whereas this person cannot start at that
level and work backwards because at that
those that architecture and simply does
not arise for that person but in terms
of collective processing at this deeper
level they're both on the unequal basis
and then the only other thing that I'd
like to potentially ask people to
consider is the other thing I'd like to
actually have people consider is a
potential that as this architecture gets
laid down in the organism and let's say
that we have a
kind of an error or confusion in this
mapping here and so as the organiz
architecture gets laid down the organism
is in some kind of pressure to find the
solution to this this not so efficient
or not this this thing that's not that
is it's not having adaptive fit and so
there are two strategies that the
organism can go through the organism can
if they're lucky find it directly but
let's say this adaptive fit is some kind
of cultural shadow so let's say instead
of this fit being a individual problem
it's a cultural shadow so let's say the
cultural shadow is a developmental bias
and a developmental bias is that
progress hierarchal progress equals
growth so this is basically the Western
bias growth toward goodness
so as the organism is coming out of
let's say conventionally blue stage of
development and realizing that realizing
that just following the rules doesn't
work that's going to create an
evolutionary or not an evolutionary
developmental tension to go into another
strategy and to complexify so now you
complexify make an object out of the
previous stage and you complexify into
orange let's say because this is what
the society the cultural conditions
offer you have this level but then
sooner or later after you get a job and
a wife and
two houses and five cars and your
existential crisis has not gone away
then that produces a developmental
tension to get even more complex and
let's say you realize duh it's about the
people stupid and so then you make an
object out of the previous stage and
your architecture gets more and more
complex because this is the structure
that the society offers at the next
level and then because that still hasn't
fixed this one problem that produces
developmental tension to move even into
even more complexity so there's a sense
in which one could argue that the
architecture of the human organism the
human cognitive development ego
meaning-making is a complex adaptive
system a cognitively adaptive system
that whose strategy is to make meaning
that seems coherent but this development
can't solve existential problems and
essential problems are more embodied
more evolutionary they don't seem to
follow developmental systems but they're
more like emergent types of processes
and the emergent processes and they all
depends upon the ability to insight
these deeper structures and shift them
and this is where you see complete
transformation in the individual and in
oftentimes in many cases this shift this
that changes this existential problem
gets people off the spiral of increasing
complexity and what you see is you see
simplicity on the other side of
complexity so you seize things you start
to use words like wisdom rather than
knowledge building so for me that's how
a little overview of this conversation
around the developmental levels both in
terms of Fisher's skill set what insight
means which is different than the
cumulative development of capacity and
how development can be a an advantage in
in some respects but in many respects is
itself can present an obstacle to deep
insight processing